Guide to the Helen Forbes Collection on Medical Wives
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Helen Forbes collection on medical wives
1947-1969
Ms Coll 31
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
This collection documents some of Helen Forbes's activities as a medical faculty wife in the mid-twentieth century. Papers include lists of which faculty wives were responsible for daily student teas; account books and statistics on attendance at teas; newspaper clippings and other information on the annual Aesculapian Frolics; bylaws and a small amount of information and newspaper clippings on the activities of the Medical Dames/Wives; lists of married students; and a recetion for the retirement of Medical Dean Vernon Lippard in 1967 that Mrs. Forbes helped to organize. Among the items is a Yale Medical Wives Association certificate conferring the degree of P.H.T. (putting husband through) to wives of graduating medical students.
Forbes, Helen Allen, 1906-2003
Yale Medical Dames
Yale Medical Wives Association
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presumably donated to the Historical Library by Helen Forbes.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Allen Forbes, wife of medical professor and assistant/associate dean for education, Thomas Rogers Forbes, was a leader among medical faculty wives, organizing daily afternoon teas served by faculty wives to medical students; acting as a perennial sponsor and advisor for the annual Aesculapian Frolic, a benefit dance held by first year medical students; and serving as a sponsor for the Medical Dames or Medical Wives, an organization for wives of medical students. Yale Medical Dames appears to have been an early 1950s offshoot of Yale Dames, an organization for the wives of Yale graduate students. By 1960, the group was called the Medical Wives Association. During much of this period, most male medical students were married and there were only a handful of female students.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents some of Helen Forbes's activities as a medical faculty wife in the mid-twentieth century. Papers include lists of which faculty wives were responsible for daily student teas; account books and statistics on attendance at teas; newspaper clippings and other information on the annual Aesculapian Frolics; bylaws and a small amount of information and newspaper clippings on the activities of the Medical Dames/Wives; lists of married students; and a reception for the retirement of Medical Dean Vernon Lippard in 1967 that Mrs. Forbes helped to organize. Among the items is a Yale Medical Wives Association certificate conferring the degree of P.H.T. (putting husband through) to wives of graduating medical students.
Medical students -- Connecticut; Medical students -- Social life and customs; Physicians' spouses -- Connecticut; Forbes, Thomas Rogers, 1911-1988; Lippard, Vernon W., 1905-; Yale Dames; Yale University. School of Medicine
- Student teas, 1947/48-1950/51 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Student teas, 1951/52-1954/55 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Student teas, 1955/56-1958/59 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Student teas, 1959/60-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aesculapian Frolics, 1947-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Aesculapian frolics, 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account book for student teas and Aesculapian Frolics, 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Account book for student teas and Aesculapian Frolics (includes Frolic invitations), 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Yale Medical Dames/MedicalWives Bylaws, 1954/55 and 1962/63 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Medical Dames/Medical Wives, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Medical Dames/Medical Wives Newspaper clippings, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lists of married medical students, 1948-1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Retirement reception for Dean Vernon Lippard, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)